Guide to the Spargel Production Rosie the Riveter Media Collection OH.081
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Spargel Production Rosie the Riveter Media Collection
2010
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Spargel Productions (Firm)
OH.081
1.8 Linear Feet in two manuscript boxes and one record carton
70 videodiscs (dvd)
70.55 Gigabytes in 102 computer files
This collection consists of interviews of women who entered the industrial workforce (automobiles, shipbuilding, aircraft manufacturing, electrical equipment manufacturing, and transportation) during the years of World War II (1939-1945). Interviews we were created on digital video for use in the Spargel Productions new media project "The Girl With The Rivet Gun." Topics covered include gender relations and discrimination at work, union experience, industrial work, family roles, transitioning from rural to urban environments, race relations, and post-war employment experiences. Interviews were taken in English and transcripts are available for all interviews.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Rosie the Riveter film project was conducted in conjunction with Spargel Productions, LLC and the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives beginning in 2010. The accession number associated with this collection is 2010.014.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of thirty-three interviews with women who entered the industrial workforce (automobiles, shipbuilding, aircraft manufacturing, electrical equipment manufacturing, and transportation) during the years of World War II (1939-1945). Topics covered include gender relations and discrimination at work, union experience, industrial work, family roles, transitioning from rural to urban environments, education, race relations, and post-war employment experiences.
Biographical / Historical
These interviews were recorded as a part of a collaborative media project by Spargel Productions and New York University's Tamiment Library. These oral histories were created on digital video and portions of them are used in the Spargel Production new media project "The Girl With The Rivet Gun." They are being preserved at the Tamiment Library.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Working class women -- History.; World War, 1939-1945.; Factories |x Employees.; Gender discrimination.; Gender identity -- United States; Race relations -- United States.; Equality |x Economic aspects |z United States.; Consumerism.; Trade unions |z United States.; Sexual Orientation |z United States; Automobile industry workers |z United States.; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States -- Personal narratives.; African American women -- Economic conditions; Sex discrimination against women.; Women -- Employment -- United States.; Women in the labor movement -- United States; Women labor union members -- United States.; Oral histories (literary works); Rural conditions.
- Jerre Kalbas, 2010-02-17 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-001, Box 3, Folder 1, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-001, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_1)
- Esther Horne, 2010-02-19 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-002, Box 3, Folder 2, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-002, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_2)
- Violet Johnson, 2010-04-14 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-003, Box 3, Folder 3, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-003, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_3)
- Idilia Johnston, 2010-04-14 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-004, Box 3, Folder 4, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-004, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_4)
- The Baltimore Rosies, 2010-04-16 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-005A / OH-05-005B, Box 3, Folder 5, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-005A / OH-05-005B, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_5)
- Susan Taylor King, 2010-04-16 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-006, Box 3, Folder 6, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-006, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_6)
- Bonnie Gifford, 2010-05-06 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-007, Box 3, Folder 7, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-007, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_7)
- The Robey Girls, 2010-05-07 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-008, Box 3, Folder 8, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-008, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_8)
- Lucetia Jane Tucker, 2010-06-28 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-009, Box 3, Folder 9, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-009, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_9)
- Signe Nakashima, 2010-06-27 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-010, Box 3, Folder 10, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-010, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_10)
- Mary Anne Diamond, 2010-06-27 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-011, Box 3, Folder 11, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-011, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_11)
- Mildred Sargent, 2010-06-27 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-012, Box 3, Folder 12, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-012, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_12)
- Evelyn Davidson, 2010-06-27 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-013, Box 3, Folder 13, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-013, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_13)
- The Carters, 2010-06-27 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-015, Box 3, Folder 15, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-015, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_15)
- Mazie Mullins, 2010-06-26 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-016, Box 3, Folder 16, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-016, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_16)
- Dorice Hamilton, 2010-06-27 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-014, Box 3, Folder 14, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-014, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_14)
- Idamae Mason, 2010-06-28 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-017, Box 3, Folder 17, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-017, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_17)
- The Powells, 2010-06-26 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-018, Box 3, Folder 18, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-018, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_18)
- Edith Lyons, 2010-06-26 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-022, Box 3, Folder 22, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-022, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_22)
- The Mathauser Twins, 2010-06-26 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-019, Box 3, Folder 20, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-019, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_19)
- Arkie Huffman, 2010-06-26 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-020, Box 3, Folder 19, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-020, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_20)
- Shirley Clark, 2010-06-28 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-021, Box 3, Folder 21, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-021, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_21)
- Francis Ellis, 2010-06-26 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-023, Box 3, Folder 23, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-023, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_23)
- Arlene Crary, 2010-06-26 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-024, Box 3, Folder 24, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-024, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_24)
- Catherine Gaultier, 2010-06-26 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-025, Box 3, Folder 25, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-025, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_25)
- Eileen Tench, 2010-06-26 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-026, Box 3, Folder 26, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-026, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_26)
- Mabel Myrick, 2010-06-25 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-027, Box 3, Folder 27, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-027, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_27)
- Nell Young, 2010-06-25 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-028, Box 3, Folder 28, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-028, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_28)
- Winona Gillespie, 2010-06-26 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-029, Box 3, Folder 29, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-029, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_29)
- Thelma Edgar, 2010-06-26 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-030, Box 3, Folder 30, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-030, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_30)
- Marion Yagoda, 2010-07-12 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-031, Box 3, Folder 31, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-031, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_31)
- Angeline Fleming, 2010-07-12 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-032, Box 3, Folder 32, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-032, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_32)
- Eva Chenevert, 2010-07-13 (Box 1, Disk OH-81-033, Box 3, Folder 33, Box 2, Dvd OH-81-033, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_81_ER_33)